Register of the Ukrainian subject collection, 1882-2010
Hoover Institution Archives
Ukrainian Subject Collection,
1882-2010
XX799
10 manuscript boxes, 7 videotape cassettes (5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Memoranda, pamphlets, serial issues, proclamations, broadsides, leaflets, flyers, election campaign literature, and video tapes, relating to various aspects of Ukrainian history, mainly in the Soviet and post-Soviet periods, and especially to events leading up to establishment of Ukrainian independence in 1991, and to subsequent Ukrainian politics and elections.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Memoranda, pamphlets, serial issues, proclamations, broadsides, leaflets, flyers, election campaign literature, and video tapes, relating to various aspects of Ukrainian history, mainly in the Soviet and post-Soviet periods, and especially to events leading up to establishment of Ukrainian independence in 1991, and to subsequent Ukrainian politics and elections.
Access Points
Ukraine--History; Ukraine--Politics and government--1991-; Elections--Ukraine; Ukraine; Soviet Union; Video tapes
Container List
- Subject File, 1948-1994 (Box 1)
  Reports, studies, election campaign literature, and miscellany. Alphabetically arranged by subject.
  - Ukraine
    - General
      - Printed matter. "Memorandum From the Free Ukrainians in Great Britain to the Prime Minister," April 5, 1956 (Folder 1: 1)
      - Miscellany (Folder 1 :2)
    - Elections, 1994. Serial issues, leaflets, flyers, and election campaign literature (Folder 1: 3-4)
    - Foreign policy. Ukrainian Foreign Policy, Organization of Ukrainian Nationalists, Scottish League for Euro- pean Freedom, Edinburgh, 1953 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Foreign relations
      - Poland. Ukraine and Poland - A Memorandum of the Ukrainian National Council to Mr. Dean Acheson, Ukrainian Information Bureau, Augsburg, Germany, 1951 (Folder 1: 6)
      - Soviet Union
        - The Muddled Waters of Falsification: Pamphlets, Dnipro Publishers, 1985 (Folder 1: 7)
        - Ukraine and Soviet Russia, Ukrainian National Council in Exile, 1948 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Working class - Ukraine. Timchenko, V., Ukraine Today: The Working Class, Politvidav Ukraini Publishers, Kiev, 1986 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Youth - Ukraine. Bulatezki, Yu., The Future Belongs to the Youth, Politvidav Ukraini Publishers, Kiev, 1985 (Folder 1: 10)
- Videocassettes, 1988-1992 (Tapecabinet Tape cabinet)
  Seven videocassettes relating to various events in the Ukraine.
  - #1 - Signing of the Ukrainian-Russsian agreement; Minister of Foreign Affairs Anatolii Zlenko and Kozyrev press conference; Ukrainian National Guard; First National Congress of the Ukraine; press conference on the independent referendum, December 1, 1991; Minister of Foreign Affairs Konstantin Morozov press conference; establishment of diplomatic relations between the Ukraine and Lithuania; parliamentary debate with Leonid Kravchuk, January 28, 1992; ceremonial pledge of allegiance to the Ukraine of Ukrainian reserve officers, January 19, 1992; Third Congress of the Ukrainian National Movement (Rukh), February 28, 1992; film entitled "Through History to the Present" by Mohylan Academy (Tapecabinet Tape cabinet)
  - #2 - Ukrainian student anti-Soviet demonstration on the anniversary of the October Revolution, 1990; dismantling of Lenin's statues in Stanislawow and Lwow; demonstration and student march on Kiev's Parliament building; arrival of the Patriarch of Russia in Kiev (Tapecabinet Tape cabinet)
  - #3 - Ukrainian student protest action/hunger strike in Kiev, October 1990 (Tapecabinet Tape cabinet)
  - #4 - Ceremonnial transfer of the ashes of Wasyl Stus from Siberia to Kiev (Tapecabinet Tape cabinet)
  - #5 - Ceremonnial raising of the Ukrainian national flag in front of the Kiev City Council building, Union of Ukrainian Writers building, and Independence Square; arrival of Russian Vice President Rutskoi and St. Petersburg Mayor Sobchak; First Congress of Ukrainian Officers Union meeting in Kiev during the Moscow coup d'etat, August 1991 (Tapecabinet Tape cabinet)
  - #6 - Viacheslav Chronovol and Mykhail Horyn interview, 1988 (Tapecabinet Tape cabinet)
  - #7 - Proclamation of Independence, July 16, 1990 (Tapecabinet Tape cabinet)
- Incremental Materials, 1882-2010 (Box 2-10)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described. Contact us at hooverarchivesinfo@stanford.edu